<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yale J Biol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Yale J Biol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">yjbm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YJBM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0044-0086</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1551-4056</issn><publisher><publisher-name>YJBM</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6430178</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">yjbm921139</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group><series-title>Focus: Attention Science</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Restoring Attention Networks</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>Michael I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>Mary K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghassemzadeh</surname><given-names>Habibollah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Department of Psychology, University of Oregon, Eugene OR</aff><aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>To whom all correspondence should be addressed: Michael I. Posner, University of Oregon, Email: <email>mposner@uoregon.edu</email>; Mary K. Rothbart, University of Oregon, Email: <email>maryrothbart@yahoo.com</email>; Habibollah Ghassemzadeh, University of Tehran School of Medicine, Email: <email>hghassemzadeh@gmail.com</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>92</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2019, Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The attention networks of the human brain have been under intensive study for more than twenty years and deficits of attention accompany many neurological and psychiatric conditions. There is more dispute about the centrality of attention deficits to these conditions. It appears to be time to study whether reducing deficits of attention alleviate the neurological or psychiatric disorder as a whole. In this paper we review human and animal research indicating the possibility of improving the function of brain networks underlying attention and their potential clinical role.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Attention networks</kwd><kwd>alerting</kwd><kwd>executive</kwd><kwd>orienting</kwd><kwd>pathology</kwd><kwd>theta</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Neuroimaging has allowed researchers to determine with increasing precision the brain areas involved in many human activities. Prominent among these has been the study of brain networks of attention. In this paper we describe the potential utility of this knowledge for the diagnosis and treatment of common neurological and psychiatric illnesses involving attention.</p><p>In our previous work we have identified three different brain networks related to the functions of attention [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. These are:</p><p>(i) Obtaining and maintaining the alert state, involving the brain&#x02019;s norepinephrine system including the locus coeruleus in the pons and frontal and parietal cortical areas.</p><p>(ii) Orienting to sensory stimuli, involving both ventral and dorsal frontal and parietal areas and subcortical areas of the superior colliculus and pulvinar.</p><p>(iii) The executive attention network that controls voluntary responses (Executive attention) involving the anterior cingulate, anterior insula, and underlying striatum. (See <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>;[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].)</p><p>These networks play a strong role in the regulation of behavior, both in the control of positive and negative affect and of the sensory input, and also give rise to consciousness of content and voluntary behavior. Imaging brain networks of attention have allowed us to identify the dominant neuromodulator of each network and to study genes related to these modulators. (See <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>;[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].)</p><p>By use of the Attention Network Test (ANT) (see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) scores for each of these attention networks can be obtained individually from children and adults [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>ANT scores have also been used to compare patients suffering from various conditions with normal groups. Abnormal scores for each network of attention have been associated with mental disorders. We summarize these associations below and in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s2"><title>Attentional Pathologies</title><p>Attentional difficulties are frequently associated with brain injury and with many psychopathologies. Without an understanding of the neural substrates of attention, systematic efforts to remedy these attentional problems have been difficult. This situation may change with the application of our understanding of attentional networks to pathological issues. In the volume <italic>Attention in a Social World</italic>, [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], many forms of pathology briefly summarized in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> are discussed in greater detail. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and the references cited there provide details on the central importance of attention to each of the pathologies. We do not think a one to one correspondence between network, disorder, and symptom is a complete story. Many disorders involve more than one network and often the networks change in the development of the disorder. For example, Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) appears to involve alerting early on and later a deficit in executive attention. Moreover, disorders have multiple symptoms. In <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> we use the most prominent connections between network and disorder and describe a typical symptom of the disorder.</p><p>In this paper, we attempt to tie the brain networks revealed by imaging studies to underlying cells and their connections found in various animal models. We have recently reviewed evidence for the role of attention in obsessive compulsive disorder [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Repetitive concentration of attention upon a potential failure appears a key feature of this disorder. Animal models have suggested that abnormal loops between anterior cingulate and striatum may be involved in Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD) [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The reactivation of this circuit may underlie the problem of repetitive attention to negative events.</p><p>Similar findings occur in a variety of other anxiety disorders [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Anxiety disorders often involve unreasonable fear (see <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In an effort to link brain networks to underlying cellular mechanisms, a mouse study has found that stimulation of a circuit from the amygdala to the striatum either by laser stimulation or by inducing a reward can improve extinction of fear [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, anxiety disorders have been identified with reduced thickness of the anterior cingulate and insula cortex in early life [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) and insula are key nodes in the executive attention network which undergo extensive development in childhood [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similar efforts link the executive attention network to underlying cells, neuromodulators, and genes [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>Stimulating the Brain</title><p>Understanding attentional networks may set the stage for possible treatments of disorders involving deficits in brain connectivity related to attention. We have been carrying out studies designed to test whether such treatment is possible. Our work began with studies of meditation training [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], we found that one month of meditation training altered the white matter connections in areas surrounding the anterior cingulate. We speculated that the alteration of white matter was due to the strong theta (4 to 8 Hz) rhythm found over the frontal midline following training [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>To test this idea, mice were bred so that neuronal output of the anterior cingulate could be excited or inhibited with laser light (optogenetics) [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] We implanted lasers in the anterior cingulate of the mice and found that for mice stimulated with low frequency rhythms so that the output neurons of the anterior cingulate showed a rhythmic increase in spikes, there was an increase in oligodendrocytes (cells that create myelin) and a decrease in the ratio of axon diameter to axon diameter + myelin (g ratio). Mice who had low frequency stimulation showed less fear and more exploration than did un-stimulated controls. This was demonstrated in a box that contained dark and light compartments. The stimulated mice spent more time in the light than controls. These findings show that connectivity can be improved by low frequency rhythms such as those produced by meditation training. Moreover changing the properties of white matter pathways surrounding the anterior cingulate reduced fear and improved exploration [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>The optogenetic method requires procedures that are too invasive to allow testing in humans. We sought to determine if there is a method for non- or minimally invasive stimulation to increase intrinsic theta range oscillations in the ACC [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We used sensory (auditory) input, neurofeedback, and electrical stimulation presented with and without a task that also stimulated the ACC. In the electrical condition we used alternating current at 6 Hz and 100 milliamps delivered by a set of 10 electrodes over the frontal midline. One minute of auditory or electrical stimulation was alternated with a minute of no stimulation. Only the minute with no external stimulation was used to assess the effects of the input on intrinsic theta levels.</p><p>Comparing the three methods [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], electrical stimulation while performing the Attention Network Test [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] was the most effective in produced significant increases in theta during a minute of non-stimulation following a minute of electrical stimulation. The 6 Hz auditory stimulation also appeared to increase theta, but this was not significant statistically.</p><p>In this study all participants used the same generic set of electrode locations previously, shown by simulation to activate the ACC [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. A new study compared these generic electrode locations with individual ones chosen using the anatomy from structural MRI to construct a different head model for each participant [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. We hypothesized that individual electrodes would be better than generic electrode sites. Our first study of the executive attention network used the anterior cingulate along the frontal midline as the site of stimulation. We also wished to be able to determine if brain areas with lower intrinsic theta than the ACC would also show an increase in intrinsic theta by appropriate choice of electrodes and a task. To test these hypotheses we compared theta rhythm induced in the ACC and in the primary motor area by both generic and individual electrodes location. In each case choosing a cognitive task that also activates the chosen brain area. The results generally favor the use of individual electrodes particularly for the ACC location. Using individual electrode locations with electrical stimulation plus appropriate task we found significant increases in theta in both of the tested brain areas.</p><p>The next step in our plan will be to test our hypothesis that we can improve white matter in areas around the ACC. We will use 20 sessions of electrical stimulation plus task and compare before and after diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) to measure Fractional Anisotropy (FA) and calculate changes in g ratio as we have done in the mouse [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. If our hypothesis of white matter change in the human brain was to be confirmed, we, or perhaps others, can use this method in actual clinical cases where white matter degeneration or loss is a likely cause of the abnormality.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Clinical Applications</title><p>Our published work to date indicates that degree of white matter change is limited. In mice, the change in g ratio following a month of stimulation is about 5 percent [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]), and our MRI meditation studies have shown about 10 percent change in fractional anisotropy [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Moreover, the Attention Network Test is improved by training by approximately 10 percent of the improvement in reaction time found during development between 7 years and adulthood [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Thus, 10 percent may serve as an upper bound of the change we might expect. It is unclear whether a 10 percent change would be sufficient to improve disorders involving white matter, or whether it will provide benefits in skilled performance for those without such disorders.</p><p>Some published data favor the idea that addiction disorders might benefit from improved white matter. We [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] studied a group of smokers who showed reduced connectivity between the ACC and striatum when compared with a comparable group of non-smokers. The participants were recruited to reduce stress and did not necessarily have an intention to quit smoking. Nonetheless two weeks of meditation training improved connectivity and led to highly significantly reduction in smoking [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Although further tests are needed, the restoration of white matter efficiency appeared linked to reduced smoking.</p><p>In this paper, we have reviewed recent discoveries about the brain networks of attention, and the opportunities for rehabilitation they may make possible. Specific attentional networks based on imaging and neurophysiological research are being associated with the symptoms found with various neurological and psychiatric disorders (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). There is little doubt that connections surrounding the anterior cingulate play a critical role in the voluntary control of emotions and thoughts [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>Research in mice shows that low frequency stimulation can change white matter and reduce anxiety [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The intrinsic theta rhythm of the ACC can be increased by external electrical stimulation conducted while the person carries out the ANT [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We believe that other brain networks can also be modified in a similar manner. Methods are being explored to improve the functioning of these brain networks in animals and humans. We do not yet know whether or to what degree any of these methods will help to alleviate disorders related to white matter loss. However the current advances in this possibility support research designed to address whether they will work and what will work best.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Research supported by ONR grant N00014-17-2824 and N00014-15-2148 to the University of Oregon.</p></ack><glossary><def-list><def-item><term>ANT</term><def><p>Attention Network Test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ADHD</term><def><p>Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OCD</term><def><p>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ACC</term><def><p>anterior cingulate cortex</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Research on attention networks as a model for the integration of psychological science</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Psychol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<issn>0066-4308</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17029565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The attention system of the human brain: 20 years after</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>.<issn>0147-006X</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheese</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Voelker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Developing Attention: Behavioral and Brain Mechanisms. Adv</article-title>. <source>Adv Neurosci (Hindawi)</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>405094</fpage><issn>2356-6787</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25110757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCandliss</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Raz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Testing the efficiency and independence of attentional networks</article-title>. <source>J Cogn Neurosci</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<issn>0898-929X</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Attention in a social world</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghassemzadeh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Mechanisms of response prevention and the use of exposure therapy for obsessive-compulsive disorder</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychiatry</source>
<volume>2/1</volume> 30 April <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graybiel</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Toward a Neurobiology Review of Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11144344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghassemzadeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anxiety and Brain Networks of Attentional Control</article-title>. <source>Cogn Behav Neurol</source>. Forthcoming.<issn>1543-3633</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Correia</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Graybiel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gossens</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Amygdala- ventral striatum circuit activation decreases long-term fear</article-title>. <source>eLife</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>12669</fpage><issn>2050-084X</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaczkurkin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soriras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (in press) <article-title>Association between Dimensional Fear and Cortical Thickness in Youth American Journal of Psychiatry</article-title></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fjell</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walhovd</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuperman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Multi-modal imaging of the self-regulating brain</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>19620</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<issn>0027-8424</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23150548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Short term mental training induces white-matter changes in the anterior cingulate</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>16649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<issn>0027-8424</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20823222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Short-term meditation induces changes in brain resting EEG theta networks</article-title>. <source>Brain Cogn</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<issn>0278-2626</issn><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24632087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piscopo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weible</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Niell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Changes in white matter in mice resulting from low frequency brain stimulation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>27</issue>):<fpage>6639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<issn>0027-8424</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><mixed-citation publication-type="conference"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weible</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Piscopo</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Niell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Rhythmic Brain Stimulation Reduces Anxiety-Relate Behavior in a Mouse Model Based on Meditation Training</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the US National Academy of Sciences</source> 114/no10 <fpage>2532</fpage>-<lpage>2537</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voelker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Comparing methods to improve intrinsic theta in the anterior cingulate</article-title>. <source>Dev Cogn Neurosci</source>. submitted.<issn>1878-9293</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>EME</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rech</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turovets</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Slow-Frequency Pulsed Transcranial Electrical Stimulation for Modulation of Cortical Plasticity Based on Reciprocity Targeting with Precision Electrical Head Modeling</article-title>
<source>Frontiers in human neuroscience</source>. <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>, DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3339/fnhum.2016.00377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27531976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stikov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wandell</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Modeling and Measuring the Myelin g-ratio Proceedings International. Society of</article-title>. <source>Magn Reson Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage><issn>0740-3194</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voelker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbart</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A polymorphism related to methylation influences attention during performance of speeded skills</article-title>. <source>AIMS Neurosci</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<issn>2373-7972</issn></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Brief meditation training induces smoking reduction</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the US National Academy</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>13971</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boord</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhyastha</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Askren</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Executive attention networks show altered relationship with default mode network in PD NeuroImage</article-title>. <source>Clinical</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><mixed-citation publication-type="web-page"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darby</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Joutsa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <source>Lesion, network localization of free will Proceedings of the National Academy of Science USA</source>
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1814117115">www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1814117115</uri></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1<sup>*</sup></label><caption><title>Brain areas and Neuromodulators Involved in Attention Networks.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NETWORKS</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>STRUCTURES</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MODULATOR</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Orienting</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superior parietal<break/>
Temporal parietal junction<break/>
Frontal eye fields<break/>
Superior colliculus<break/>
Pulvinar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetylcholine</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alerting</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locus Coeruleus<break/>
Frontal and parietal cortex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norepinephrine</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Executive</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior cingulate<break/>
Anterior Insula<break/>
Basal ganglia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dopamine</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Adapted from Posner, MI. Attention in the Social World. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2012</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Disorders Associated With Attention Networks.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Attention Network</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Condition</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Symptoms</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alerting</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aging<break/>
ADHD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disorder (a)<break/>
Sleep disorder, hyperactivity, concentration (b,c)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Orienting</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autism<break/>
PTSD<break/>
Neglect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disengage deficit (d,e)<break/>
Difficulty in disengaging from fearful stimuli (f)<break/>
Reorienting in contralesional direction (g)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Executive</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety Disorders<break/>
Depression<break/>
OCD<break/>
Personality Disorder Borderline<break/>
Schizophrenia<break/>
Substance Abuse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difficulty inhibiting fear (h)<break/>
Dwell on negative ideation (i)<break/>
Recurring thoughts, images or behaviors (j)<break/>
Negative ideation, lack of control (k)<break/>
Hallucinations (l)<break/>
Compelled behavior (m)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(a). Fernandez-Duque D, Black SE. Attentional networks in normal aging and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. Neuropsychology. 2006;20:133&#x02013;43. (b). Halperin JM, Schulz KP. Revisiting the role of the prefrontal cortex in the pathophysiology of attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder. Psychol Bull. 2006;132:560&#x02013;81. (c). Johnson KA, Robertson IH, Barry E, et al. Impaired conflict resolution and alerting in children with ADHD: evidence from the ANT. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2008;49:1339&#x02013;47. (d). Landry R, Bryson SE. Impaired disengagement of attention in young children with autism. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2004;45:1115&#x02013;22. (e). Towsend J, Courchesne E. Parietal damage and the narrow spotlight of spatial attention. J Cogn Neurosci. 1994;6:220&#x02013;32. (f). Levy BJ. Controlling intrusive memories. Unpublished doctoral dissertation University of Oregon, 2008. (g). Posner MI, Walker JA, Friedrich FJ, Rafal RD. J Neurosci. 1984;4(7):1863-1874. (h). Ghassemzadeh H, Rothbart MK, Posner MI. Anxiety and Brain Networks of&#x000a0;Attentional Control. Journal of Cognitive and Behavioral Neurology. Forthcoming. (i). Drysdale AT, Grosenick L, Downar J, et al. Resting-state connectivity biomarkers define neurophysiological subtypes of depression. Nat Med. 2016;23(1):28-38. (j). Ghassemzadeh, Habibollah. Mechanisms of Response Prevention and the Use of Exposure as Therapy for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder. International Journal of Psychiatry. 2017;2(1). (k). Posner MI, Rothbart MK, Vizueta N, et al. Attentional mechanisms of borderline personality disorder. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2002;99(25):16366-70. (l). Wang KJ, Fan J, Dong Y, Wang C, Lee TM, Posner MI. Selective impairment of attentional networks of orienting and executive control in schizophrenia. Schizophr Res. 2005;78(2-3):235-41. (m). Tang YY, Tang R, Posner MI. Brief meditation training induces smoking reduction. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013;110(34):13971&#x02013;5.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The Attention Network Test uses a target surrounded by flankers see A for target types. Before the target appears cues are given see (B) for cue types. Reaction time is the dependent measure and bottom panel shows the scores for the alerting, orienting and executive (conflict) network (adapted from Fan <italic>et al</italic> 2002 [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="yjbm_92_1_139_g01"/></fig></floats-group></article>